

# ARTEM DONETS

# PH.D./RESEARCHER/PROJECT TECHNICAL MANAGER ENGINEERING MANAGER/RENEWABLES EXPERT

#### CONTACT

1-825-994-8528

donets.ive@gmail.com

https://don-ar.github.io/

10 Brentwood Common NW, T2L 2K8, Calgary, Canada

### SOFT SKILLS

- Problem-solving skills
- Project management skills
- · Effective communication skills
- · Emotional intelligence
- · Great attention to detail
- Technical skills
- Delegation skills
- · Time management skills
- · Ability to maintain a work-life balance
- Ability to provide effective feedback
- Ability to foster trust between team members
- Ability to motivate team members

#### EDUCATION

## Ph.D. of Engineering Science

Institute for Renewable Sources of Energy

2011-2017

#### Master of Science, Power Engineering and Automation

National Technical University of Ukraine, Igor Sikorsky Kyiv Polytechnic Institute

2009-2011

#### Bachelor of Science, Power Engineering and Automation

National Technical University of Ukraine, Igor Sikorsky Kyiv Polytechnic Institute

2005-2009

#### LANGUAGES

#### PROFILE

13 years of experience in complex engineering projects including solar, and wind power plants with a total capacity of approx. 2 GW. Implementation and managing the best practices approach during all project phases such as BIM, digital twins, etc. **Certified Senior Renewable Energy Expert by DEWA** (Dubai electrical and water authority)

P.Eng. Certification APEGA in Alberta province (in process).

Certified Engineering/Project Manager by Ukrainian authorities. Excellent organizational and coordination skills and ability to juggle all aspects of a project, from early-stage business development through design, construction, commissioning, and quality assurance till technical taking-over to O&M. Also, actively participate in scientific (publications, conferences, etc.) and R&D life as a Ph.D. in the renewable energy sphere.

 $Developed, Designed, Constructed, Commissioned, etc.\ multiple\ renewable\ power\ plants\ megawatt-class:$ 

Wind > 1 GW; Solar > 1 GW installed capacity.

Give me a lever and a fulcrum on which to place it, and WE will move the world!

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### **Engineering Coordinator**

TetraTech - Calgary, Canada

2023-Present

- Coordinate leadership, direction and development of the internal engineering team.
- Coordinate the overall project engineering team (internal and external) activities, ensuring project schedules are met and that the engineering team is utilized effectively.
- Prepare Project Execution Plans.
- Help develop project strategy to ensure key issues are identified early and to ensure project goals of quality, schedule and cost are achieved.
- Undertake preliminary design, energy estimates and project economics to assess the best site development scenario.
- Prepare and/or review cost estimates, schedules, risk assessment and elements of project design.
- Coordinate across the engineering team (internal and external) the design of all project elements, ensuring
  consistency in strategy and approach.
- Ensure external engineering deliverables and design meet project requirements and standards.
- Implement appropriate review processes for all elements of design, including technical, construction, logistics and operational considerations.
- Ensure all design documentation is delivered in accordance with company policies and processes.

#### Co-founder, CTO

<u>Windyfi</u> - Oslo, Norway

2022-2023

Manage the development of the web-based product which utilizes gamification, machine learning, geospatial data as well as manufacturer's equipment information to enable energy sector developers to make optimal decisions that increase the value of their project. From idea/scratch to the MVP.

#### **Project Technical Manager**

SCATEC ASA - Oslo, Norway

2018-2023

Provide full engineering and managing support for 12 Renewable energy projects with installed capacity > 600 MW.

- · Manage the detailed design process to stick to the program and budget;
- Establish a baseline for measuring the progress of engineering deliverables during the tender and the
  design process as per the SMDL and the Bi-weekly template with the lead planner this should consider
  tender and construction packages, critical construction and procurement items against the overall program
  plan;
- Ensure all requirements and technical parameters in the project documents are incorporated in the final project design via involvement in the design review process:
- Manage the Design and Cost review process to ensure cost-competitive and effective design which meets both Solutions and O&M Minimum requirements;
- Meet the baseline schedule for engineering deliverables to avoid delays in contracting or construction via active measuring of progress, and adequate resourcing;
- Successfully manage the core technical deliverables during the structuring phase;
- Establish a priority plan (with PM) for technical deliverables during the structuring phase (e.g. contracts, site studies, SOWs) given the technical resourcing constraints of the projects;
- Establish documents tracking protocols based on PTM templates for specific project requirements;
- Ensure the project program considers technical requirements;
- Conduct red-flag analysis at/before NTP to ensure that the following items are covered;
- · Detailed design completion;
- Testing, procurement and logistics;
- Sequencing and allowances for pre-commissioning, commissioning, plant testing and commissioning;

# ARTEM DONETS

# PH.D./RESEARCHER/PROJECT TECHNICAL MANAGER ENGINEERING MANAGER/RENEWABLES EXPERT

#### CONTACT

1-825-994-8528

donets.ive@gmail.com

https://don-ar.github.io/

10 Brentwood Common NW, T2L 2K8, Calgary, Canada

#### TECH SKILLS

- AutoCad, Autodesk Invertor, Autodesk Revit (BIM);
- · Matlab, Simulink;
- DIALux:
- MathCad;
- · SolidWorks, AnSys;
- NI LabVIEW;
- · Vipor, Homer Energy;
- MS Office (all packages);
- 3d's Max;
- · Wolfram Mathematica;
- Python, C++;
- Photoshop;
- · Primavera;
- Sketchup(with Skelion), Helioscope;
- PV GIS, PVWatts, PVSyst, PVDesign (Rated Power), PVCase, etc.

#### HOBBIES

A bunch of. Unfortunately, there are only 23 hours and 56 minutes in a day.

#### PUBLICATIONS

A lot of publications are in Ukrainian and international scientific journals. Sources and links to publications are available upon request.

#### CERTIFICATES

- P.Eng. Certificate (APEGA, in process)
- · Certified Senior Renewable Energy Expert by DEWA (Dubai electrical and water authority)
- Energy Independence Certificate (USA)
- · Engineering/Project Manager Certificate (Ukraine)
- Lead Engineer Certificate (Ukraine)
- SCADA Specialist (Norway)

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

- · Taking over processes and documentation such as O&M manual, quality file submission, 3rd party inspections
- Manage 3rd party interactions;
- Actively control communication with LTA (WOOD, WSP, DNV) / local partner during the structuring and
- Identify and Manage scope interface risks between FIM suppliers, PV Contractor and HV Scope of Works;
- Assist the HV Package Manager to manage the HV interfaces towards the utility promptly to secure commissioning and grid connection;
- Follow through on technical site execution:
- Create onboarding technical data pack for the site teams;
- Assist with onboarding of the technical site team, and brief members concerning monitoring of the construction against functional requirements and approved design;
- Implement clear communication and decision-making protocols with the contractor and site team;
- · Ensure that the construction team actively snags and closes MOWs during the construction phase to reduce punch list items at MC, and ensure maximum availability of the plant;
- Initiate Planning of plant commissioning 3 months before MC, and thereafter manage plant commissioning and testing according to schedule at NTP with assistance from the site;
- Assist with onsite requirements for Grid Code Compliance testing and Utility inspections;
- Support in the project close-out phase by preparing and gathering technical documents as needed to achieve TTO, to achieve TTO by COD.
- Reduce the timeline between TO and COD to the same week, or as close as the conditions of the PPA allow
- Review and monitor the closure of Minor Outstanding Works on site after COD.

#### Chief Electrical Power Engineer/ Researcher

Institute for Renewable Sources of Energy - Kyiv, Ukraine

2011-2023

- · Detail design, explanatory notes, specifications for the project, carrying out the necessary calculations;
- Develop project objectives by reviewing project proposals and plans; conferring with management;
- Determines project specifications by studying product design, customer requirements, and performance standards; completing technical studies; preparing cost estimates;
- Ensure projects are delivered in time, quality and cost targets within the agreed risk profile;
- Project delivered to the desired quality standards; Provide quality assurance on delivery of projects using appropriate project methodology, techniques and processes, throughout the entire project lifecycle;
- Oversee project planning, scheduling, communications, costing, issue resolution, risk assessment and
- Supporting feasibility studies regarding technical aspects;
- Participation in EPC contract negotiations;
- Preventing mistakes and defects, ensuring engineering best practice observance;
- Coordination of pre-sales activities between the parks division and equipment suppliers, including technical documents validation and supply contract negotiations;
- Elaboration of equipment list with cost breakdown;
- Preparing presentations for investors;
- Contribution to renewable energy science such as scientific articles, conference participation, etc.

## **Electrical/Interconnection/Communication Manager**

Hustad & Granaas - Oslo, Norway

2020-2021

Provide full engineering and managing support for a Wind Power project with 800 MW installed capacity. Key duties and responsibilities:

- Manage the detailed design process to stick to the program and budget;
- Ensure all requirements and technical parameters in the project documents are incorporated in the final project design via involvement in the design review process;
- Manage the Design and Cost review process to ensure cost-competitive and effective design which meets both Solutions and O&M Minimum requirements;
- Meet the baseline schedule for engineering deliverables to avoid delays in contracting or construction via
- active measuring of progress, and adequate resourcing;
- Successfully manage the core technical deliverables during the structuring phase;
- Detailed design completion;
- Participation in FIDIC Silver Book contract negotiations;
- Assist with onsite requirements for Grid Code Compliance testing and Utility inspections.

#### **Engineering Manager/PV Expert**

YTT Solar Resources - Dubai, UAE

2018-2019

Provide quality assurance on the delivery of projects using appropriate project methodology, techniques and processes, throughout the entire project lifecycle.

# ARTEM DONETS

# PH.D./RESEARCHER/PROJECT TECHNICAL MANAGER ENGINEERING MANAGER/RENEWABLES EXPERT

#### CONTACT

1-825-994-8528

donets.ive@gmail.com

https://don-ar.github.io/

10 Brentwood Common NW, T2L 2K8, Calgary, Canada

#### TECH SKILLS

- AutoCad, Autodesk Invertor, Autodesk Revit (BIM);
- · Matlab, Simulink;
- DIALux:
- MathCad;
- SolidWorks, AnSys;
- NI LabVIEW;
- Vipor, Homer Energy;
- MS Office (all packages);
- 3d's Max;
- · Wolfram Mathematica;
- Python, C++;
- Photoshop;
- Primavera;
- Sketchup(with Skelion), Helioscope;
- PV GIS, PVWatts, PVSyst, PVDesign (Rated Power), PVCase, etc.

#### HOBBIES

A bunch of. Unfortunately, there are only 23 hours and 56 minutes in a day.

-----

#### PUBLICATIONS

A lot of publications are in Ukrainian and international scientific journals.

Sources and links to publications are available upon request.

## CERTIFICATES

- P.Eng. Certificate (APEGA, in process)
- Certified Senior Renewable Energy Expert by DEWA (Dubai electrical and water authority)
- Energy Independence Certificate (USA)
- Engineering/Project Manager Certificate (Ukraine)
- Lead Engineer Certificate (Ukraine)
- SCADA Specialist (Norway)

#### \_\_\_\_\_

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

## **Lead Engineer**

Karbon Invest - Kyiv, Ukraine

2016-2018

Manage the design of the biggest Solar and Wind power projects in Ukraine with a total capacity of more than **600 MW**.

#### **Lead Engineer**

StarEnergy - Kyiv, Ukraine

2012-2013

- Preparation of the feasibility study and commercial proposals material to the clients;
- Develop projects for solar hot water systems and heating based on solar collectors, etc.

#### **Contributions**

- Developed the program using python programming lang, which creates \*xml forecast maquette for PV plants energy, signs it by digital signature and uploads it to the grid operator repositories according to the schedule.
- Developed the algorithms using python, pandas, numpy, etc., which improves the energy yield forecast for PV plans based on historical production data. The improvement is saving millions of dollars for PV facilities every month due to the government penalties for the deviation between actual Renewable facilities production and day-ahead energy yield forecast.
- Developed the python script which automates the adjustment of complicated AutoCad drawings based on the changes in input data. It allows decreasing time for drawings adjustment implementation from a few days to a few minutes.